Hi y'all, how's everyone doing?
Am I audible and visible guys?
Give me a thumbs up, thumbs down if you can see me, hear me out.
Great, great, thank you.
Let me do a screen share and start the timer so that we'll wait for that amount of time.
And then we'll get started with today's class.
Just do let me know if you can see the screen share too.
Great, good evening.
So guys, how was the assignment?
How was the contest?
Did you face any challenge in the contest or it was fair and simple and straightforward?
Give me a thumbs up if you have cleared it, if you have attempted it.
Easy, right?
Cool.
Great guys, I see that people who have attempted it, more than 90% of them have cleared it.
Only 1-2 people, I think they left the exam in between because their score seems to be completely zero.
They didn't attempt it.
Yeah Kabir, we'll pick it up later.
Okay, once we complete the content for the class, then I can pick it up.
I think it was okay.
Two days.
I have an announcement too guys.
Once we have enough people joining the class, then I'll talk about it.
But in between guys, I would request you one thing, right?
Who are following up?
Whenever we are learning JavaScript.
So I would ask you to follow one of the websites.
Like JavaScript info.
This particular site.
And try to read through this fundamentals and everything.
I would say every topic.
I've read this I think 3-4 times but I keep revising this stuff again and again.
Okay.
So it has 3 parts.
Basically, first is JavaScript language.
Then you can explore browser events, everything.
That we'll be introducing once we start with Tom.
But then there are some additional topics like if you want to read through them.
But you'll see that all the topics are clearly explained here.
I'll pin this one.
So why I'm giving you this one is that I want you to all follow up this one.
And whatever topic we are picking.
Let's say we completed variables and data type.
Go through that.
Understand that.
If you have any challenge on that one also, do let me know.
This is something site you'll be coming back and referring back again and again.
For JavaScript at least.
Because I prefer that one.
If you have any better resource.
Feel free to go through it.
Read through it.
Okay.
But in case you have doubts, do let me know.
One thing I want to make sure is that when you are preparing.
When we are going through JavaScript classes.
I hope you are following up.
You are studying the content.
Other than also with the classes.
So that whenever there is a mock interview.
Which is coming along with HTML, CSS, JavaScript.
In future.
Down the line after a month.
I want you to be confident on that.
Like from day one day.
For the first class itself.
Since it's the second class.
Highlighting that.
Be confident.
Be prepared.
Each day whatever topic we are going through.
Just go through that JavaScript info.
And try to explore and read through it.
Works guys.
Because at the last moment right.
If you again try to prepare.
Freshly for the interviews.
It would be really difficult.
So we will be doing it parallelly.
And I will try to highlight those things.
Which are like interview points.
Which are important.
Can anyone help me with dropping.
Like a text in WhatsApp group.
Like we are getting started.
I see less number of people today.
Meanwhile I will share my iPad.
Guys anyone can share WhatsApp group.
Link here.
I will pin that one too.
Would be thankful.
Meanwhile I will stop the timer.
Since the time is up.
And we will get started guys.
Okay.
So before getting started.
I have a small announcement.
So I will be on leave.
And I will see you guys later.
Bye.
I will be on leave from this Saturday.
To Friday.
Next week Friday.
I have my sister's wedding.
My own very own sister.
Elder sister's wedding.
So I have to take care of many things.
So I won't be able to take.
Your Saturdays.
And Tuesday.
And Thursday's class.
So I have requested for a replacement.
Instructor for three classes.
So I will let you know.
Who is getting assigned and what.
One thing I will make sure.
That he teaches you.
To the best quality of content.
And even I will provide.
You know my notes.
That I have taken in the previous batches.
That I will share it in the same GitHub repo.
So that you have both the things.
Works guys.
So I will give you the name of the instructor.
And everything in the Thursday's class.
Great.
So I have pinned this Whatsapp link.
Ok fine.
So guys.
Rather than writing anything in iPad.
Let's go to the code.
Since we started on JavaScript.
It's more of a coding now.
Thank you so much.
Promote that.
We will be delaying your classes right.
We want your.
Whatever we have promised.
Those to be on track.
I will be anyway sharing my code.
I will also be explaining things.
Ok.
So.
I will make sure that you know.
Rhythm is not affected.
Because I will be trying to cover those also.
And I will talk about that thing.
How it will work.
Ok.
So guys.
In last class.
We stopped at.
Arrays in depth.
So we.
Like we were exploring all the methods.
Which are available in arrays right now.
I have asked you to go through the slides.
And try to see the syntax.
And use this. Has anyone explored that one?
Did.
Do you remember that? Or like.
Did you get a chance to explore this?
Give me a thumbs up thumbs down guys.
If you didn't.
That works even. I will try to explain.
Good. I see no one.
Ok.
So one thing we will do is that.
Firstly I will revise everything.
So we remember push and pop.
What does push and pop does?
Adding and removing from the last index of an array.
Similarly unshift and shift.
Which are like removing and adding.
From the first index of an array.
Zero index.
And slice is somewhere.
If you want to cut.
A particular piece of an array.
You have to give a starting and ending index.
If you want that particular slice of an array.
It will return you a new array.
Or else if you want only like starting.
From a particular index until the end index.
You can give only the starting index.
This is what we have explored in the.
Like these methods.
Now splice is a powerful method.
So what it does is it gives an ability.
To add remove replace items.
So now let's see one of the ways.
How you can add it firstly.
So collapse is existing code.
So that we can see.
Now if you see an array of 1 to 10 is something we are having.
So what I will do.
Is that let's say I create a new constant variable.
Saying D.
And I will say that A dot splice.
Okay.
Now whenever I do splice.
If you see I am getting here in the suggestions.
Starting number and delete count.
Okay.
It can be a number or undefined type.
So what I will do is that.
Number of variables.
Let's say I want to start like.
Add items from the index 1.
And I don't want to delete any numbers.
So I will say that 0.
Then let's say I will go and.
Try to add this one.
Let's say now if you see we have 1 to 10.
Let's say it index 1 from this position.
We add 3 5's.
Let's say we do 5 comma 5 comma 5.
Okay.
Now let me do console lock.
Of this one.
And I will show you guys this one.
Node array start.js.
So.
Okay. I have too many things.
Give me a second.
Okay.
It doesn't return an array firstly guys.
So it changes the existing array.
Let me.
Comment other things.
It does return it.
Okay.
Clear.
Okay. We are getting an empty thing here.
Empty array to be.
You know.
As returned.
Okay.
Splice whenever we are doing splice right.
It will affect the exact array.
But it won't return a new array.
That is what it does.
Let's say now if you see what just happened.
No it's a splice shape.
Okay.
So.
What we are doing is like we are starting an index one.
Like.
If I write down what the parameters are.
Start index.
And then.
Delete items.
Delete number of items.
Then.
All the items.
You can say all the items.
Okay.
So what I did.
I said starting index is one.
And I don't delete any items.
So make it zero.
And add all of these three five.
Into this array.
So if you see after one.
Then it started with two three four again.
Right.
I hope this is clear guys.
How this.
It works for adding.
Similarly if you want to delete it.
Let's say if you want to delete it.
One way is like you can say splice.
And then you can say that hey.
Starting.
Like this is.
Acting as a adding.
Items.
Into array.
Let's say.
This will work as a delete.
Okay.
Now let's again we do console.log.
Let's say I clear this.
And I execute this again.
Now if you see. Firstly what we did.
We tried to add three items.
One.
And I added three.
Then I printed it.
If you see while adding again the same result.
One triple five and two three.
All these things.
When I'm trying to remove all these things.
Which I added just recently.
And it is also removing it.
Is this clear like how this works.
Like adding and removing.
Guys thumbs up.
If this point is clear like adding and deleting it.
Okay now.
Then there is a third thing called replacing it.
Replacing items.
In an array.
So when you want to replace right.
Now you have to give.
Like first.
Like index like let's say.
I want to replace items from 0th index.
And I want to add.
Like to replace two items.
From there.
Then I'll say that can you give me.
Something like 12 and 13.
So this is supposed to make.
And build an array.
Like 12 and 13.
Then 2 then 3.
And then 4.
What we are trying to do is like we are starting from 0th index.
And we are trying to replace two items.
With 12 and 13.
Let's see this once I do a console log.
Clear.
If you see.
It's 12 13.
4 5 6 7 9 10.
Right.
This is what our output is.
So I hope this.
Is clear like how this works.
And what are the parameters it is taking.
Sorry arguments it is taking.
And how we are passing it calling it.
Any doubts guys.
Any doubts in all the array methods that we have discussed.
If you have anything do let me know.
Then I'll go to today's class.
Which we want to pick it up.
No doubts.
So let's get started guys.
Today's.
Content with something.
Like we'll explore things in the objects first.
Objects.js.
Since we have dealt with an array.
Like how we can add delete remove items.
From the array.
Similarly we'll see in terms of objects.
So let's build some.
One object.
Called as you know.
Have you.
Is anyone fan here from the.
Movies like.
So.
Who is the main character guys.
Who plays around like.
Like Marvel movies.
Like.
I thought so Abhishek.
And everyone thinks.
I don't know.
He is a cool guy.
Who is the leader guys.
Who is the leader.
Captain America right.
Let's let's build.
Captain America.
Once Iron Man died I feel like.
Marvel has ended the story right.
So it doesn't.
Show up the same same like.
Interest like I don't have to.
I don't find same interest.
Even Captain America doesn't exist.
No.
Does anyone remember the character name.
Captain America what was his.
Marvel still.
You know they are building.
Like.
Some series I've seen one series.
Steve Rogers right.
Now and then.
What could be his age guys.
How long he lives.
Any dialogue do you remember.
Any dialogue. When.
165.
Then let's say.
If I write allies.
Who are his allies.
You can give his name.
Team name.
Go by names.
Let's try to remember the names.
Winter Soldier.
Give me the name.
What was the name of Winter Soldier.
Tony is someone.
I can write.
Yeah Bucky.
Then.
What was the role of Scarlett Johansson.
In that.
I mean character name.
Black Widow is fine.
What was.
Actual name.
Natasha right.
Do you remember this Natasha.
Then.
Our hulk.
No one mentioned hulk.
That's a banner.
Okay.
So these are the like let's say least.
Basic allies.
We also have a Thor.
We'll write a Thor.
Now.
Let's say what would be the address of this.
Captain America guys.
What would be the address of Captain America.
Let's say I give a country.
What could be the country.
By default I'm getting United States.
Because everything.
Happens is like starts problems.
In United States itself.
And let's say if I go for city.
It's Brooklyn right.
Rather than New York it's Brooklyn.
Then.
Let's say I give some pin code.
In the US they call it a zip code.
And let's say.
Five digits.
And.
Let's say we also have something like.
Is Avenger.
Is Avenger leader.
Is he leader for the Avenger team guys.
Right.
Then let's say.
I am just adding a function.
Random function.
I.
Console dot log.
Captain says.
Hi.
Okay.
Now.
What I just did.
Is that we built an object.
With all the existing data types.
We have discussed.
Isn't it.
Do you see an object in object.
Do you see an array inside.
Do you see a number.
String boolean function everything.
That we just discussed.
Right.
Is.
Is anyone having any doubt in this.
Like how is this possible or anything.
Because this is a custom data type.
How you do it.
Simply without using classes in JavaScript.
That you can keep on adding any key.
Value pairs directly.
Okay.
Now.
Once we have defined it.
Now let's say three things.
Accessing.
Accessing the keys.
Accessing the items.
You can say items of.
Object.
Then.
Updating.
Items of object.
Adding.
The items.
Into object.
Then.
Deleting.
Object.
These are the four operations.
That is something possible on any data right.
Which we call it as crude.
Right.
Something that you can do on any.
Like database or data type.
Create.
Update and delete.
These are the four operations.
Now we will try to do this all four operations on.
Object and we will see that how we can do it.
Or how we can read it.
Now one of the simple way.
If you want to read anything right.
Out of object.
So let's say first thing is.
Like you have to get a hang of this object.
That object name is Captain America.
And using dot operator.
You can access all the items in it.
Like let's say hi.
Address, age, allies, name.
Let's say I print the name.
And also what I can do is that.
I can say console.log.
If I want to execute a function inside it.
Let's say Captain America dot.
I say this is like.
Say hi.
It's a function.
So I can call this function.
Is this point clear guys.
Like how you can access an item.
Out of an object like using a dot operator.
Pretty straight forward simple right.
Now.
How can you update it.
If you want to update anything right.
Let's say.
What we will do is that for updating.
You know at the moment when.
There was a new captain for the.
Marvel right.
Someone like Wonder Woman.
Some character came in.
I don't remember her name though.
New person came in.
So then this Captain America.
Was not a leader.
But she was an Avengers leader then.
So what you can do is like.
You can go to Captain America dot.
Is Avenger leader.
Then you can make it false right.
So you can update.
Existing values of an object.
Using this way where you can assign.
New values using like equal to operator.
This is like assigning a new.
Similar you can do anything.
Up to it.
Right you can update it.
Then if you want to add it.
Let's say if you want to add.
Items into an object.
One way is like you have to give.
The same object name.
Then you can give like let's say.
I want to say the movies he appeared in.
And let's say I have an array of movies.
Then.
I'll keep something like civil war.
Then let's say I have something like.
Endgame.
Endgame then.
Age of Ultron.
Then Infinity War.
So what I'm doing is like.
Whatever new key I want to add into object.
That thing is something that I'm.
Trying to get a new.
Since it is not available.
Even using dot operator.
I can give new values and assign the new values to it.
Okay.
Your first Avenger.
Is this clear guys.
Say hi will be returning undefined.
We'll check that Abhishek.
But it's like accessing updating.
Delete is like sorry.
This three functions are clear right.
How we can do operate on an object.
Similar way you can.
You know you can always delete something like.
Let's say.
I want to do a console log here before.
Deleting it.
I say Captain America.
Object.
Then let's say I want to delete.
Movies out of it.
You know to delete right.
You can use a delete keyword itself.
You can say delete keyword.
Then you can say object name.
Movies whatever things you want to delete.
Or data.
Whatever data you want to do it.
So this way you will be able to delete.
The things.
Let's say.
I say added.
Movies.
Console dot log.
Remove movies.
Then.
Console.
Log.
Updated.
Later status.
Right now let's say what things are.
Going on here.
What I'll do is like I'll go into this file.
And execute this one.
If you see.
Let's explore this.
One by one.
First thing.
Please come again once.
I'll come back again I'll revise everything some bit.
Let's see this one guys.
One by one again.
So firstly we built an object.
Then we have assigned.
All the types of properties in it.
Then we are trying to access it.
If you want to get a name.
Yeah.
Right.
We wanted to access the name.
Now using a dot operator you will be able to access it.
Then after.
We went into console log and we thought to.
Execute function.
And.
If you see here.
That execution got happened.
It says captain says hi.
Then if you see.
We updated the status of East Avenger leader.
Is equal to false.
And if you see updated leader status.
Here.
And East Avenger.
Is like false.
Then we went on to.
Add something like movies into the.
Same Captain America object.
And now if you see.
Movies got added here.
Then.
We went on to delete.
Now after deleting.
The object is still same.
Like I mean.
After removing movies.
Is this example clear guys.
Like how this is working.
Basically.
Everything is done through a dot operator.
You can access it.
You can update it.
For delete only you have to give a special.
Keyword called delete.
Then you have to access whatever property you want to delete.
Or object you want to delete.
Okay.
I hope no doubts in this.
No doubts.
One final thumbs up guys.
I need few more thumbs up if you want me to go ahead.
So we covered up to an extent.
For both.
Arrows and objects.
What if.
We assign undefined.
Undefined is not something you should assign at any time.
Abhishek.
Okay.
I see one thumbs down.
Shubham.
Do you have any doubts?
I hope you don't.
If you have anything do let me know.
I will take your doubt.
Okay.
I will revise it.
So what we were doing.
Is that we created an object called.
Captain America.
In this we added few set of fields.
Key value pairs.
Where name, age, allies, headers.
High function.
So we covered all the possible data types that we discussed.
Okay.
Once we discussed this one.
Then we thought to see like hey.
We have seen on array how we can add delete and remove replace everything.
How can you do it?
So I have written four examples.
Like how can you access update and delete.
So if you see.
If you want to access any item.
And print it or like print it.
Then you can say that object name.
A dot.
Any key that you want to access it.
Okay. If it is a function you have to execute it.
If it's a key directly you can access it.
Similarly if you want to update it.
You have to get that particular object.
Key and assign a new value.
And if you want to add all together.
A new item into that object.
As a new key value pair.
You have to just say that object dot new key.
And then the whole value.
It will be added.
Similarly if you want to delete you can use delete key one.
And delete any key that you have.
Is this clear Shubham?
Can we go ahead?
Yeah updating zip code.
Let's say if you want to update the zip code.
Let's say I'll do it here.
If you see I have
1 2 3 4 5
I'll do Captain America dot.
Then address dot.
Address dot city.
Dot zip code.
I'll say instead of 1 2 3 4 5
Say 5 4 3 2 1.
And I save it.
Let me re-execute this one.
Node object dot js.
If you see.
Once we are updating it.
It got updated here.
Like updating status.
Is this clear?
Okay nice.
Moving ahead guys.
Since we have explored.
Good element of these two things.
Now it's our time to go into the functions.
And understand different keywords.
Generally interviews try to.
Irritate you with those keywords.
There's nothing much logic in it.
But we have to understand a few things.
So I'll try to show you how.
What are these things that you have to remember.
Those are keywords.
Let's say there's something called.
Function statement.
Does anyone know what function statement is?
Function and declaration.
Similarly you have.
Function expression.
So these are the like.
You know different words they use it.
Like do you know this do you know that.
But you know in a way.
You might have used many times.
But you don't remember it.
It works that way.
Let's say anonymous function.
Then you have named.
And then you have.
And then you have named.
Function expression.
Then let's say.
You have.
I have a function.
Ok.
These are the list of functions that are existing.
We'll explore one by one and we'll see.
Now whenever one say that.
You know function.
Statement and declaration.
The both are talking about same thing.
Ok.
Now let's say if I write down here.
Function declaration.
And statement.
Both are talking about same thing.
Which is like you just say function.
Sorry guys.
Say hi.
I'm using that still.
So.
Let's say who is wishing whom.
I use from and to.
I use console log.
From.
Is wishing.
Hi.
To.
Ok. So let's say this is a function.
Now whenever you declare a function.
What we have just declared a function.
And this particular thing is itself called as a function statement.
Is this point clear.
Whenever we say function declaration or statement.
We are talking about same thing.
So I hope you won't be confused.
Whenever someone is talking about.
What is function declaration or statement.
In future.
Right.
So now.
What these two things are called guys.
What these two things are called.
From and to.
And.
Anyone in the class.
What this from and to are called.
Parameters.
Do you guys agree if I call them as a parameters.
Function parameters to be specific.
Right.
No. Let's say.
I say say hi.
And I say that let's say.
I'll be shake.
And let's say.
So now.
The expected output would be.
Abhishek is wishing hi to the Ratan.
Right.
No.
But.
What these things are called guys.
What these things are called.
What is Abhishek and Ratan.
Function arguments right.
So whenever.
You are calling.
Executing that particular thing right.
So you say that you are passing an arguments.
Into it.
Okay. And whenever you are receiving.
Inputs into a function those are called function.
Parameters.
Okay.
I hope you would remember this case a difference.
Between parameter and argument.
Whenever you are executing it.
You are generally passing whatever things you are passing.
Those are called arguments.
But whenever you are accepting those are called parameters.
If you see.
Whenever I am highlighting also it shows parameter.
Parameter like you know.
Now if I go here.
Let's see.
It doesn't show anything.
But these are just called as arguments.
These are the parameters.
This is a function declaration and statement.
I hope these points are clear till now.
Let's open this terminal.
And just execute it for sake.
Node function.
JS.
So we are able to execute that one.
But moving ahead.
Now let's say.
Parameters are like variables.
Yeah.
So those are like any data type you can declare it.
You can accept and you can play around inside the function.
Okay.
Now.
Going ahead guys.
Then there is something called.
This thing is what we call this one guys.
When I say say hi and I am passing parameters.
What we call this?
Anyone?
Can I say function invocation simply?
Function calling or function invocation.
Right.
So.
Let's remember these keywords as this one.
So I am trying to say that hey.
This is not something that you don't know already.
But it's just you know.
Sometimes people get confused in the pressure of interview.
So I am just giving you those names.
So that whenever you come across these names.
You will remember them.
Okay.
So.
Now let's go to function expression.
When I say expression.
It means that I am storing a function inside a variable.
Let's say.
I say say hi expression.
Okay.
I can still copy this one.
Or else I can still copy this one.
And I can put it here.
Can remove this name.
And I can say from.
Say hi expression.
Okay.
So.
You can do in JavaScript is like as if you see.
When we declared objects just now.
Earlier.
We were able to assign.
You know.
Function to a particular key right.
In the same way.
Even in the JS you can.
You know assign a function to a particular variable name.
Whatever variable you have defined.
So whenever you are defining this.
Whenever you are attaching a function.
To a particular variable.
That is called as function expression.
Is this clear.
Like you can say if I want to be specific.
You can say.
That function is anonymous right.
Function doesn't have a name.
Okay.
So whenever you don't have a name.
You say them as an anonymous function expression.
Okay.
But let me again.
Copy this.
And say hi.
Expression.
Re-execute this one.
Give me a second.
If you see.
I am able to print.
Say hi.
Expression.
Called as.
Function expression.
I declare it here.
And I say one.
And I say as a say hi.
Okay.
Now.
Whenever you do this.
Even if you want to execute.
Am I audible now. Voice breaking.
Guys can anyone confirm me.
Again.
Now better.
Okay.
Thank you guys.
Thank you for letting me know.
But now.
So what I was talking about.
Have explored function expression.
If you see here.
When we declared this one.
We didn't name anything this function yet.
Like we just defined function.
And then we gave parameters and its function body.
Now if you go and say.
Even create a name right.
Even if you give this name.
It's something called as named function expression.
Okay.
Let me do one thing guys.
Let me do.
Again like I'll try.
Can you hear me now.
Better.
If you face again.
I'll switch my wifi network.
To the something other thing.
Okay.
If you face that challenge.
Let me know. I'll try to rejoin the class.
Okay.
So.
So whenever you are using.
You know name to a function.
Which are assigned to a variable right.
That is called as named function expression.
Like here I am saying say hi.
But that doesn't really play any role guys.
Like if you even.
If you want to execute this function.
You are supposed to call this function.
Say hi from expression one.
And let's say I also give.
Here keyword.
Just to know this one.
And I copy.
This whole thing.
I paste it here. I say one.
Okay.
So there is no difference as such.
Like if you see I am getting from expression one.
Expression.
And simple function.
Okay. So this is called as.
Anonymous.
Function expression.
To be write this word.
Anonymous.
This is called as a.
Named function expression.
Any doubts guys on this.
Like these are like just.
Functions that we have rewritten.
Again and again.
Like.
With the different conventions.
Guys.
Are you able to follow up.
Or my voice is still breaking.
Yeah both are same.
Even if you want to call it.
Like let's say even if you want to call it.
You are using the same variable name.
But here.
Whenever you are declaring a function.
Attaching a function.
If it is having a name.
It is called as a named function expression.
Or it will be called as.
Anonymous function expression.
But from the execution point of view.
There is no change.
That's just a keyword guys.
Even whatever I am writing it down.
I believe you already know it.
I am just explaining those keywords.
That I have written on the top.
Because whenever you see these keywords.
For the first time in interview or any place.
You get confused.
So I am trying to remove that jargon.
From your head.
This is really simple and straight forward.
So then there is something called as.
Arrow function.
Which you can say.
I say hello.
And I just declare a function this way.
Without a.
Function keyword itself.
Now I avoided.
Function keyword also.
Now I can say again use the same thing.
Let's say.
Copy and paste.
I will remove this one.
And I will add.
The syntax.
So how many of you are familiar with this syntax.
Whatever I have written.
Have you seen this in any language earlier.
No one.
Guys Java 8.
If anyone worked with Java.
Functional expression.
How would you use to write.
That is the same syntax.
So for the people who haven't seen right.
So what we are doing here.
It's a new way.
And this was introduced in year 6.
So this.
Will solve some problems.
Will come to that problems.
What we call it as what problems this.
This particular sort of function was.
Solving in future.
But as of now I'm just introducing.
Different types of declaring a function.
Or calling them.
Ok.
So this is also one of the way.
You can declare a function. If you see.
What are types of ways are there.
You can call a particular function.
As like a function declaration.
Or statement.
Function expression.
Named function expression.
Then arrow function.
All of them are still doing the same problem.
It's solving the same problem.
Isn't it.
They have like too many names to it.
Just too many names.
Ok.
This file I just created so that you can go.
And revise the stuff.
Like you know.
Just in a snap of a time.
Ok.
Now.
There is one more thing guys.
You know in JavaScript functions are called as.
First class citizens.
Have you heard this keywords.
Or.
First class function.
Ok.
So you know.
These two keywords.
They use it like.
To say.
Like you know.
In JavaScript functions are really powerful.
And they are called as first class citizens.
Or first class function.
So why is it so.
Why is it so they are called so many things.
So because.
In JavaScript right.
Functions can be used.
Functions.
Can be used.
As methods.
Right.
Guys.
Is my network failing again.
Just want to check with you.
Ok. No right.
Yeah.
So functions can be used as methods.
And as variables.
And.
Can be passed.
Into function.
And can be returned.
From a function.
So let's say what.
What do exactly mean is that.
Functions.
If you see.
If you remember this like.
If you go for any other languages.
Right. If you go for any other languages.
Like the language you might have worked with.
A particular.
You know.
Function might not accept.
Function as a parameter.
And you know.
It cannot return a function from a function.
Right.
Have you seen those like use cases.
Can be done in any language.
If you remember in Java.
Whatever functions you declare in the class.
You cannot return a function from a function.
Right.
And you cannot accept even a function.
Because you have to define a type.
Right. So these are not possible.
No. But in JavaScript.
All things are possible.
So how this is possible.
I will show you this example.
Let's say I.
I declare a function.
An arrow function.
Let's say that.
This thing will return something called as.
Let's say say hello.
So what I am doing is.
I am returning a simple string.
Whenever someone executes this one.
Now let's say I create another function called.
Hello world.
And I say.
Whatever param it receives.
Okay.
And I will say that. Hey.
What param you are receiving.
Return that param.
Okay.
Now.
If I say console.log.
Let's say hello world.
Inside that param I will pass hello.
What I am supposed to return guys.
What I am supposed to return here.
What it will come here.
Inside the console.log.
Say hello. So how many of you think that.
This thing will be written.
If you think say hello will be written.
Give me thumbs up.
Okay. I see many people are thinking.
Right. Say hello will be written.
Guys just think of this one.
How would you execute this function.
By passing whatever parameter you are passing.
Right.
I am passing of.
Parameter called as hello.
But did I execute anywhere hello.
Still.
Did I execute hello.
No right. Then how will I.
How it will return say hello.
Let's see what it will return first.
Clear this console and.
Let's execute this one.
Now if you see.
This hello world.hello is returning a function.
So I just wanted to show.
This statement that hey.
You can pass a function into a function.
And you can also return a function from a function.
Is that clear.
Like this two statement.
Can be passed into a function.
Can be returned from a function.
Is this statement.
Justified guys.
Right.
Now if I want to execute this.
Whatever returned function is there.
One way I can do is like I can call again.
Whatever function is written.
I can call again.
Or else I can always do something like const.
New func.
Let's say new func.
And I can say again.
Hello world.
Right.
Then you can say.
Call hello.
And you can say.
New func.
Of this one.
So always you can do something in two steps.
But also you can do something in one step.
Like whatever function is written.
Execute that.
So let's say execute.
Now it is printing say hello.
Is that clear. Like why it was not coming earlier.
Now it is coming.
So.
This is the reason why.
In JavaScript you know functions are called as first class
citizens. Whenever I say first class citizens.
Are the people who are having
higher powers in society.
Like if you go and search.
Key word like first class
citizens.
Okay.
If you see.
A member of a class of individuals
that receives a fair treatment.
Or like a top.
Or you can say.
Let's say.
If you see. The president is a first class
first citizen of India.
I mean generally we are talking about
someone who is having more powers.
Or more things right. More speciality.
Than other
existing thing. This is the reason why.
And why it is.
What type of powers it is having is like
this statement. It can be used as
a method. A simple method like
whatever we have declared first.
But it can also be used as
a function expression.
And it can accept
functions as a
parameter and can also return it from
there. Is this clear.
Like why we are calling these two
keywords.
Why we are using these
two jargons to these functions.
Guys how many of you
are clear with this point.
Or whatever we have learned.
So I see one thumbs down.
Give me a minute and
check.
I see one thumbs down.
Sambit is it
clear or like.
Do you want
me to repeat. Anyone do you want me to repeat
this one.
Okay let's repeat this one guys.
Let's repeat this one.
So what we have
understood here till now is that
different types of.
Okay let's
see this guys. Let's see this from the starting
again. So we have declared different
types of you know
different jargons we are trying to explore
that on a function.
So first we declare a simple function
and this function can also be called as
whenever you are declaring it. It's a function
declaration or function statement.
Right. And this is what we understood.
Then we say that hey whatever
things you are receiving inside these two
brackets are called as function
parameters. So these are parameters in general.
Whatever you are writing in between
two braces those that is called as function
body. Okay.
And if you want to execute any function
you call that as a function
invocation and whatever things you pass
between the value calling
those are called as arguments.
Okay. In the same
way we went on to
you know understand different types
of you know declaring a function
that we went to to understand like
there is something called an ominous
named function. An ominous function
right. Expression. So where you
have declared a function and
assigned it to a particular variable
without name.
Then it is called as an ominous function expression.
Okay. Remaining
all the definitions still the same.
Going with the named one
whenever you are assigning a particular
function to a variable let's say if
that particular function is also having a name
then it is called as a named function
expression. Okay.
Then in ESX
to make it clear right
to add a better
syntaxes you can also avoid
the function keyword and do
the job of whatever you are doing.
Just you have to add this like equal
to and greater than symbol
and then you can execute this part.
Okay.
So the same body same
parameters same list of arguments.
Now after discussing
this what I was saying is that hey
in JavaScript you know people call
functions as a first class citizens
or first class functions.
The reason is because
functions are really powerful
in JavaScript. How
powerful they are like how they
are showing their power is that
functions are so multiple
that they can be used as a method
and as also variables.
And can be passed
into a function and can be can also
be returned from function.
Okay. For that reason
I
have written one of the example
called I created a function called
hello it is returning a simple
statement called string called say hello
then I went on to create
another function called hello
world which is accepting param and returning
it. Now whenever
I call let's say firstly
I say hello
world
dot hello whenever
I'm doing it I'm supposed to get
hello here back
as a return output
of this one whenever I'm calling this.
What this hello is
hello is this particular function.
Now in order to execute this function
then I'm again calling it back.
This is what we have done.
Okay.
Guys is this clear now
or better.
Can we move ahead.
I hope like you revise this one
it wouldn't be that straight forward if you
revise this one right. Nothing
technical or anything as we have done
it here it's just a different names.
Right. Cool.
So guys
going to one of the important
topic and you can
say a bug
in JS. Okay.
Let's say I do console dot log
of a
and I try to execute
this file.
What would be the output guys.
What should be the output.
Undefined.
Shashank
think of
it.
How many of you think
not defined like if you
if you're okay with undefined go with thumbs
up if you're not if you go with not defined
go with thumbs down.
Thank you guys.
So as we discussed this one
in last class undefined
versus not defined.
So
if I try to execute this one
let's say clear
node
hosting dot
JS since
A is not yet
output as a not defined.
But what if
but what if
I declare
where A equal to 10.
Yes. What do you
think the output would be.
If I declare where
equal to 10.
Think of it this guys.
So I'll give you
you know
three possibilities. It can go
with undefined.
It can go with not defined.
Or it can print something called as 10.
Right.
So let's say this is first
guys vote for this one
first second
and third.
Whatever you wish.
Most of them say
not defined.
I see one.
I see three.
Okay. Three. One.
Cool. So I see a different
sort of answers. Okay.
Now let's understand
what's happening here. Let's go
understand what's happening here.
So this will you know
will blew your mind when I execute
this one.
Okay.
What I just got guys.
No.
Undefined what is like
undefined is something that I got.
Let's say if I go
and create a new
index.html.
And I link this
with HTML.
Let's say
we are discussing
something called as hoisting.
H1 tag.
And let's say
I try to link script
tag.
Source
host.
Okay. What I'll do
is I'll open this in live server.
I'll
copy this one.
Okay.
Let's say
I open inspect.
I open console.
Okay.
I'm getting undefined value here.
Firstly.
So
are you aligned like
is it working as expected
till now?
Is it working as expected?
Do you think this is working
as expected?
No right.
Because
if I go from execution
point of view.
Whatever we have understood that
in JavaScript or HTML CSS
executes from top to bottom.
When I reach this line
A is not existing
in this file right above this one.
But we are saying that
A is undefined instead
of not defined.
This is our doubt. Isn't it?
Right.
If I repeat again.
So we know that code
execution starts from top and it ends
at the bottom.
JS is something called
a single threaded. It will come in the future
why we call it a single threaded and
what all those things are there.
When I'm printing this
A doesn't exist on the top.
So A shouldn't be
undefined.
But going back to here.
Coming back.
Opening something called as this file
hoisting.
I'll put a debugger. So guys if you
I'm also teaching you how to debug the code
parallelly. If I put a debugger
and refresh it.
If I refresh it
and I go and check something called as a
global. Let's say global
it's a window. Now if you see this
somehow
in global space
or global memory you can say
A is coming up right.
A is assigned undefined.
You see this.
So we'll understand
the phenomenon how JS
works actually.
How this JS works in general.
Now
let's go
to the iPad first.
I'll write down one
example firstly.
Okay. Let's say
I have something like
where
A equal to
where B equal to
20. Okay.
And let's say I have
something called as function
add.
A comma B.
And inside this
what I'm doing is returning
a statement.
Let's say not returning statement first directly.
Let's say something we have called
answer
A plus B. Since we
are using where let's use that where as
of no. And let's say we
are returning answer.
Right.
What I'll do is like I'll
use something like let's say
where
result which will be R.
I'll say add
10 comma 20.
Or let's say we say that
it's A comma B.
And let's say where
R1 equal
to add
R comma B.
So guys can you give me what is the output
for this one.
When the code is executing from the top
to bottom.
What should be the output?
Of this two variables
var1 and var2.
Let's say I'm printing
those printing them
console log. Let's say I'm doing a console
dot log.
R comma R1.
Now
30 and 50 right.
Because it is 10 plus 20
30 and 30 plus 20 50.
Right. Now this is what
are expected. But now
let's understand how this is
executed behind the scenes first.
Let's see how this is. So
firstly in JavaScript
right.
Execution happens in two steps.
First is
memory creation.
Or you can say memory
allocation.
Then it says that code
execution.
Okay. This is a phase
one. This is a phase two.
Now whenever
you want to think from an execution
point of view right. How the code is being executed
behind the scenes. You can always
expect there is something like this one.
Okay. Let's say I have
let's say
a box.
A box will have two
steps.
First something is called as
memory
creation.
Once memory creation
is done then code execution
will come.
Now this
each box whenever it is created
this box is called as execution
context.
So
whenever your code is being executed
there is something called execution context
created.
In that first
memory creation phase happens
then it goes for the codex.
Now whenever memory creation phase is
happening what does it happen is that
it will see all the existing
variables whatever variables are there
it will check because it
needs some value to be assigned in future
right because A is a value B is a
value R1 R2. Similarly
what it does it say it is having
all the things it will what it will
do it will store something like
A B
then it will store something
like add
add function
then it will have R
R and R1.
So what it does it
sets firstly
it sets something called as undefined.
It sets something called as undefined.
For functions
it will store whole function.
This is undefined.
Again
this is undefined.
So whenever
we are creating the memory
space whenever we are creating
memory creation right
the global
execution
context for this one will
have A undefined
B undefined
then add
function
then R
then R1 so all this will be
there. Is this clear
guys with memory creation
step first what happens when you go behind
the scene it will skim through the
whole code of that particular
file it will see all the variables
and function it will assign
memory like assign memory it
will initialize variables
with the default values these are the
default values this is the default value
this is the default structure that's how
it does when code execution
happens now the file is getting
executed from line by line
what it does it goes and check that hey
this is the line one so it is asking
me to assign A equal to 10
so it will go and say
that hey assign A
equal to 10 let's say it will go
and say A equal to 10. Now once
it is executed this will be
removed and
this undefined will be updated
with 10
okay now once
this line one is executed then
it will go back and check the line two
says that B equal to 20
then again here in
the code execution it will read this
line B equal to 20 then
before completing this
task it will go and update in
the memory that hey B
is equal to 20 update it
okay is this
clear guys
how A and B value is actually
created A equal to 10 and B equal to 20
anyone having any
doubts till now
okay now
where are you going for the next step
if you see here
we are just declaring
it we are not executing this one right
yet
is there any
invocation being done in the steps
wherever I have put a bracket
are we calling
that function yet are we executing
that function yet
no right so when it is going
through execution phase of this one it doesn't
do anything that
exist in memory still
okay now
then we have something
like this
where I am checking
that R is undefined now
it goes and execute where A
equal to add of
A comma B no
how it will understand A equal to
add of 10 comma
no now comes the existing
part I mean new
interesting part what happens
is whenever you are calling
a function
it will go and create
another box for it
inside this box again you have
memory creation
and code execution
because
so the here
the whenever you are creating
this again for this function
R now let's say here what are
the variables that need to be initialized inside
R which are like A
equal to 10
B equal to 20
right and answer
answer is coming from where
if you see here we have declared
a variable called answer
whenever we are coming with answer
it will set value as
undefined
is this clear guys this point
till now
ok
that's the reason why
I have created this as a step one
then I will keep on
keeping adding things ok
now when
it is undefined now comes the code
execution path now what it does it
goes and check that hey I
have to come to this line
execute A plus B
then it will go and say that hey
can you get A plus B value
which is 30 update
this value undefined as
30 so what it will do
it will remove this something called as undefined
and update is as
30 and
once this is 30 update it as
30 it is supposed to
return it is supposed to
return that answer when it is being written
this execution context
will be closed and the
value of R will go from
here to here and update
as
this is clear guys
how R value 30 is calculated
from behind the scenes in JavaScript
now I will try
to re show this one how it will
works for R1 ok
let's say now we are on the R1
it will see
it will see that hey I need a
R1 and
it is something like add A
comma B now let's
say I clean this up
add it is
what is our value of R
which is 30 comma 20
right this is the values being
passed again now
whenever this is being done
again for executing this new
function which is R1 is
calling a new execution
context will be created under
this box
let's say I create a new execution context
which is called as MC
memory creation
code execution
and let's say now A
value has become 30 because
we are passing R value that is what
we are doing here right R is
30 then
once this is 30 then B equal to
20 answer is
still undefined
and then it calculates A plus
B which is 30 plus
20 50 update
answer as 50
once it goes
it updates this value in the memory
as 50
once it is updated
then this
context will be closed and
this particular value of undefined
will be updated as 50
okay
let me scratch this one and update
values okay
this is clear guys how
this code flow works
from memory execution
point of view
so I will show this in live to you
like how this is working how
can you see this example
same example let's
let's implement the same logic
that you see here
the same example okay where
A equal to B and this all this
things let me write that function
here
going back here
let's remove this
where A equal to
10 where
B equal to
20 then let's say I have
function add
A comma B
then I return let's say
const or let's say
where answer
equal to
A plus B
and return answer
return answer
and I will store
const R
as a result
first result add
A comma B
and const
R
1 S
add R comma
B
and to console
log this one console
dot log R comma
R1 this is what
we have written
now see actually in browser how
this is executed okay guys
going back to
this code now
let me remove this debugger as of
now clean this
up if you see 3050
is getting printed that is fine now
but let's see whatever we have seen in ipad
let's go step by step
I will put a debugger here
and I will refresh it now if you
see
let me update
this as a var firstly
I want to show you few things
okay
let me
refresh this page
I still see
output as 3050 fine
now let me
refresh again
if you see here what I have
told you is like in the memory creation phase
if you see I have stopped
code execution at line 1 itself
okay
any piece of the code is not
executed it
but if you go and see there is something called global scope
you will see that hey
A equal to undefined
then B equal to undefined
and let's say if you go and see that
there is an add function also declared
in the memory okay
you see it is requiring
its name is add
and it will do whatever steps like
it will take A and B as a parameters
and it will execute it
but do you see this is a memory creation phase
that is the same thing that we have seen right
you see
initial memory creation phase A,B,R and
R1 let's say I will show you
R also if I go down below
in the global context
see R and R1 all things are
assigned undefined isn't it
is this point clear guys memory creation part
that initially
the file will be
created and the memory will be
allotted to them the default memory is
like undefined for the variables if it is
a function the whole function will be
attached to it now once
this is done okay once
this is done there is something like
a call stack
a call stack is there so it says
that hey I am executing
it call stack shows you where
the particular line is which line is
being executed now if you see
we are stopped
at line number 1
let's say I put a debugger everywhere
okay we are at line number 1
we are
executing line number 1 as soon as I click
play
that line number 1 is executed we went
to line 2 but if we go in a global
space and see the value
of A is assigned as a 10 because the line
1 code is executed and B is
still undefined is this clear
like code execution happens step by
step once the memory is created
that's how variables are assigned
now
the next step let's see if I if you
if I click play again if you see
B value will be updated
B value got updated 20 now
if you see this line 4
and 5
is still not executed we
keep that part of code this code is
executed because we didn't call
we didn't call that function
we haven't executed but we went to line
number 8 now because in the call stack
if you see we are executing
line number 8 here is where we are
invoking the function and what
are the values we are passing if you
see the values that we are passing
is something called as 10
and 20
now see this amazing thing
what happens now if you see line
number 8 if I click play
again in the call
stack
here did you
see something then there is something
called add is created
this is a separate box that
I talked about this is a new window
new box like
this is the box right if you
see this this box particular box that
I was talking about
I need this
so this box
got created how you can see this one
inside this add
stack right now if you see inside the local
scope as I have told earlier
like a value will be 10 b value
will be 20 and answer
will be undefined initially
right that same thing has happened
a 10 b 20 parameters
are there answer is undefined
right is this clear
like what's happen like how this
function for every function
a new execution context is created
now if you see in the next step
answer will be calculated
answer is
calculated as 30 and that is being
written now once this is returned
from the call stack this box
will be cut like as I
have cut it this particular box right
as I did this box cut
and I updated it in a same
way from the call stack add will be
removed like it's like same
again it's a same stack data structure
first in first out
okay sorry
first in last out
okay once I execute
this if you see I got it
line number 9 but
if I go in a global stack
I can see the value of R
when I scroll down
if you see the value 30 is updated
right now if I
go further now if you see below
this are the list of functions
by default browser provides you
but again
on the line number 9
we are standing here
now if you go and see in this
whenever R1 is created again
a new execution context box will be created
this one if I go and click
play again new
execution context will be created for
this one add and the values
are like now 30 and 20
and answer is still undefined
and once I click play
answer is updated
as 50 and then
it will be returned
once it is returned it will
update in the global context for the
R1 also
see this is
50 then we are
printing it to directly into the console
that's a fair step
right
did you understand the workflow guys
how behind the scene it is working
anyone having any doubts
does anyone want me to repeat
because I went down so slowly because
I wanted you to understand
explaining on ipad and
parallel in live
ok if anyone having
any challenge right I would ask
them to you know
go and try to rewatch
the lecture it will really give you
good understanding of it ok
few things guys again
going back to the same question
now
let's say I do console log
console log of z
and I declare var z
equal to b
now
what would be the value of z guys
now I want all of them
giving me right value
what would be the value of z
when I do console log of z
undefined right
I hope behind the scene you got
the idea why we are getting undefined
right
so this point
for this point now
ok now
let's go
into something any website
any website you pick it
let's say I go and pick javascript info itself
and I search something called as
hoisting
they don't have directly
but let's say I go and do
hoisting in javascript
I search it now
and there is an article
ok let's say I
go and open this
if you see read this part right
let's not
go this one they have written long content
let's go for simple one
if you see what they say that
in javascript variable can be declared
after it is been used
right we have told
we have done it console log
we have used it then we have declared it
in other words variable can be used
before it has been declared
or initialized to say so
right
or
in order to understand this you have to understand
something concept called as hoisting
hoisting in javascript is a default
behavior of moving all the declarations
to the top of the current scope
or to the top of the
current script or the
current function
this is what they are giving
a description
but if you
remember this particular sentence right
you might not be able to
get the complete context of it
even whenever you are
explaining hoisting or any concept
I would ask you to remember
this particular flow right
hey why we are moving on to the top
of the particular file we are not actually
moving it to the top
that is being executed in two steps
firstly
memory will be created for each
and every variable and functions and objects
then
code execution starts
and when memory is already created
that memory creation phase itself
is called as a hoisting
since memory is already created
you can use those variables even before
that code is executed
for which variable you are assigning the value
this is clear
like would you be able to explain hoisting in your own
terms using taking any
example rather than this definition
where you are moving the items on to the top
clear right
so I hope everyone
got the better idea
of hoisting
because you can go and explore
any definition
you can go and explore any definition
it's up to you
but what's happening
behind the scenes is something
that I have explained
okay if I say
like if I say that
hey all the variables even if I
do it it will be
took to the top before executing it
it's really confusing one person
would really hate JavaScript
to understand that way
but this is what is happening
behind the scenes guys
so do you need a
break or do you want me to continue
guys do you need a
break
okay
5 minutes works
so
5 minutes
let's take 5 minutes guys if it is possible
okay
5 minutes
okay I am starting
timer for 5 minutes
take break for the 5 minutes guys
then I will close the topic of
hoisting once after the break
I have to talk about few more things then I will close it
okay
so guys see you back in 5 minutes
so
okay
guys
so
okay
you
guys is everyone back
yeah thank you guys so I hope whatever we have discussed till now that part is
clear now I want to show you a few more things few more analogies okay let's say
I create another file called as hosting 1.js okay but going back to our first
class that we have discussed when we discussed our data variables right we
have seen three ways of using variables like var let and const isn't it and let
and const were solving some of the problems that var has created isn't it
right guys now let's let's do this saw see this like hoisting how this is
behaving how hoisting is behaving with respect to if I use let and const if you
see in other example everything that I use something is called as a var okay
but now let's say let's make something like console.log of a and I declare
const a equal to 10 as per hoisting concept it should give me something
called as undefined isn't it what we have learned till now but let's execute
this one and what it says
node hoisting 1.js it gave me some error guys it gave me some error saying that
cannot access a before initialization does this look better than earlier or
earlier it was good like if I use var I was getting undefined but here to write
a better coding practice this helps better right hey you cannot use a before
initialization right or does all agree like can I have a few more thumbs up if
you agree with this like it's a better fix for hoisting issue but if this is
giving an problem and if this is giving me a problem let me show you with this
also a let keyword okay if I even use let even if I use let it still says me
the same error that cannot access before initialization so do you think here
hoisting is being applied if we for let and const you think like hoisting
concept is being applied for let and const no right how many of you think no
give me thumbs up if you think no or go with no no anyone anything works I see
people who are reacting they mean to the they think that hoisting is not applied
but as I've told you when we were learning this topic we thought we
understood that this as a hoisting is not something like where you're taking
variables onto the top it's a memory creation code expression that's a really
a basic flow but it still it happens it still does execute that way but how it
is executing and where how it is able to still you know follow hoisting is
okay let's say I link this particular file with HTML as a hoisting 1.js I
save this and let me go here okay now when I'm using let if you see this it's
already throwing an error okay it was throwing an error but if I execute this
one right I still get you know cannot access a before initialization both when
I make good in Chrome and even with node I'm getting that same error but let's
me refresh this one once no so earlier we were able to see a here itself right
if I use a var keyword do you guys agree in the global window now inside global
window there is nothing like a value assigned here okay but do you see this
script tag do you see this script tag here the value of a is already created
now but the value is unavailable they say that this value is unavailable so
whenever you say this value is unavailable right it means that you know
you cannot use this before initialize this error will be returned to us so
this it means what what we can say that this is still hoisting is being applied
that hey instead of undefined value being applied let's say even if I do
console like undefined being applied it is memory creation for a is still
happening right at least variable is created in the memory isn't it value or
like a memory memory is created for it but there is no value available right so
we can say that hoisting is still happening hoisting is still happening
but it is a happening in different something called a script now this
script right people called it as a temporal dead zone okay let's say I call
it as
temporal dead zone what do I exactly mean by this is something I'll say so
they say that hey this values are in temporal dead zone like why this are in
if I go back and I cut this and I put it on to the top this is the right way of
executing isn't it and let me play this and refresh this one once if you see I'm
having a still value is unavailable memory face is created now code
execution is happening once I execute this line one code you can see the call
stack also once I execute this the script value is updated as 10 but do
you still see here a value in global memory you don't see a value in the
global memory still right but this is working in the same as a hoisting
concept on in a first no values are available and then actual values are
applied whatever when code is executed so then it is executed and you receive
an output as 10 now why they say that temporal dead zone is because of this
script they call this like hey these are you know they're not polluting global
scope but they are creating a different scope and inside those this variables
are being created and then they are you know
and then you will be able to use them
okay is this point clear like how let and const is handling the problem of
hoisting you cannot do console log
you
okay I have to check my
give me a second guess I'll switch my network
you
I ableto hear me no
I think I have to keep my cam off for today not sure why my internet is fluctuating ok
let me try with cam on if you feel still face challenges do let me know ok ok now I'm just
trying to explain this guys on iPad I hope you can see this what is temporal red zone
ok now using where keywords right whenever you use where no this generally pollutes global space
global space memory like I have shown you in the in like here right if you see here
this is something a global space and that is belongs to browser it is affecting that
but when it coming to this let and const they are working in different area different zone
you can say ok they are not polluting this global scope even if I if you see this initialize
evaluate a equal to 10 is not by default available in the global ok it was solving a problem of
pollution of global space firstly when you use let and const there are few more differences
like as I explained earlier like re-declaration re-initialization those problems are solved now
the third problem is like when we when initially in where write keyword while writing in JavaScript
they used to use some function called IIFE have anyone heard this something called as
immediately invoked function expression right so the syntax was like function right wrapped
around inside a function that is executed like they used to write this logic the reason only
where was available whenever you write a where it was creating in a global space and it was
polluting it now why they were writing this IIFE function was as I told you earlier whenever a
function like this one like add is executed a new scope is created for that rather than polluting
this global memory right this memory will be created some memory so they were solving this
problem of global memory issue and they were writing this logic in IIFE if you see the older
code bases right you will see most of this pattern of JavaScript has been written ok so the first
problem they were solving is that hey whenever I'm declaring any variable you are polluting my
global space so I don't want you know my variables to be created in a you know global space but you
have to have your own particular space like now for them they call the space as a script space for
each thing they will have their own space is that clear firstly this point why we were able to see
this a inside the script tag guys I'm audible so is this point clear firstly I'll talk about IIFE
it's not a right time because I can give you a document on that but it's just you know whatever
things are being created inside the memory you know whatever you write let's say you write a
code of 60,000 lines inside that you'll have a functions objects and everything and whenever
it is reading through the code for 60,000 lines of variables in memory should be created it memory
phase should be done then code execution will come so that is big headache so they used to follow a
different pattern altogether to write it to fix this issue they they introduced again these two
keywords solve that problem say they say that whenever you are declaring this variables right
instead of going into the global scope we'll go into the script scope a different scope altogether
okay now I'll also show that how does it work with the example but here whenever even you are using
let and const how is thing is working how is thing is working with better enhanced error codes
right because how they enhance this error codes by default inside the library is that in JS library
is that if you are trying to initialize it says that cannot access a before initialization this
error code is coming from the library itself whenever you are using let and const is that
clear like how they are fixing this issue of error codes and this memory pollution and how
hosting is still occurring in let and const let me do one thing let me do one thing I'll try to
rewrite the same example let's say how is thing I'll copy this one I'll paste it here okay let's
say I comment this one I paste it here I say const const once let's say this one so I didn't
do anything I updated variable name here okay and still HTML hosting one is connected with
this script let's go back and you know let it get executed refresh it now the if you see if I go
to the console log still the output is 3050 still same okay but how this is getting executed will
be different if you see if I go and replay this one do you see here inside this scripts variables
are inside the script tag but in global space you don't have variables do you see what what
fix they have done right now if you see if you go and see this add function let's say if I go and
see this add function it will be still available here if you see add function is available okay
no let me show you another thing if I create an object
say first name
last name
okay no let me execute this re-execute this one
okay now do you see even the object is not initialized here in initialized here
guys okay no let's do one more thing let's do one more thing let's do one more thing now
what I'll do is that I'll say const add if I do this had okay now if I refresh this one
I refresh this one do you see add is added in the script tag instead of here in the global space
so if you go back and see the examples that we discussed earlier when I was introducing
functions right this was a older syntax then we told that hey you can assign a name like
anonymous function or the named function expression so whenever you do this you are generally trying
to whenever you use let and const you are generally trying to you know stop polluting
the global space like global variables because global space is something which wouldn't be
cleared this there is no no one working behind the scenes to clear this memory right so imagine
if you have a memory card and you don't need any most of the things but you still possess your
memory will be filled and your mobile will become slow right if RAM is completely consumed same
thing so here they try to like when you use let and const that not polluting that space and this
particular thing script whenever you are executing whenever you are doing this one this this part of
thing is called as a temporal date zone if I show you exact definition if I show you if you see this
a temporal date zone is a specific period in the execution of JavaScript code where variables
declared with let and const exit exists but cannot be accessed or assigned to any value like when I
say this it means that inside the script tag until these values are updated they cannot be used or
you know cannot be used or updated I mean they cannot be used or like until the values are assigned
to it that particular zone itself is called as a temporal date zone something that I understand
is like from the logical perspective what I mean I'm able to see inside the browser where
the JavaScript is being executed is this point here like still hoisting is happening if you
see go and do it again a Google using does hoisting happen when I use let and const
variable okay see they use in the ECMAScript block scope this is a medium dialog see he says
that I used to think that hoisting only happened to the variables declared with var but recently
I've learned that it also happens to variable declared with let and const right so he was
trying to explain what does happen with let and const here so he used that same thing cannot
access a number before initialization or the same sort of examples okay then he came to the word
called as temporal date zone okay because that is as a created inside the script tag it is not
available to you for you to access it and better error management is this clear now what do I
exactly mean by this temporal date zone or why it is not available to access it
guys is this clear like there's a differences between let const and this one so let me try
to explain you this one further okay so what we have explored when we go with this further
in depth right let and const okay is that firstly they like select const and where
hoisting is happening here also hoisting is happening okay but if you try to initialize
if you try to initialize variable before declared let and const will return errors here
if I do that same thing undefined will be written now this all confusions all this confusions are
because of h Brendan H so if you do any work in really hurry right you create this sort of
mistakes later on team sat together and build this better other management better exceptions
and they provided you a right sort of you know way of writing code is this clear guys why we
go with let and const instead of where as I see only one thumbs up I hope you understood what
hoisting is how it is working in behind the scenes is it confusing guys I try to make it
as slow as possible so I I would hope like you know you go through it you go through again like
you know recording once and try to read through the articles because I've told you like you have
to read along with me whatever topic I'm trying to teach you you have to read along with me
as per your content I'll try to explain this let's say pick this article let's pick this
article whatever article you find it read through it then you face to face channel let me know
is that is that fine Ankit because I mean how do you decide which what I didn't get your point
Ankit to use okay how do you decide to use it firstly you see if I'm if I'm writing a code this
way if I'm writing a code this way that hey I'm trying to access your variable which I didn't
even created it I'll see from the top to bottom and then I'll say I forgot it I then I say that
this one this is not a right way of writing a logic because logic works from top to bottom
the code execution works from top to bottom in JavaScript that is how we remember to address
that issues right you have to go with using let and cons let's say use a let right when you use
this let the supposed to write in a right way to execute that code in a right form the format that
you want so that's a reason why this let and cons unknowingly you are solving too many problems
behind the scenes
yeah you are supposed to use only today's world right in today's world of code whenever you're
dealing with JavaScript you are only using let and const you're not supposed to use like var keyword
okay let me write a sentence for you guys like I have this one
okay let's say I paste this one so when you declare a variable with let and const those
variables will not be accessible before initializing at that moment they'll be in temporal let zone
like in a script now let's go and explain explore IIFE pattern in JS okay
okay
now if you if you go and see this one so they are something trying to avoid the polluting a global
namespace okay generally they are trying to do this one because it will have a separate execution
context I would ask you to read this logic also I mean try to go through this one you'll understand
what I was talking about because this will be a bit advanced I don't want you to go through it
this because this is a particular design pattern that you will find if I show you why IIFE was
preferred
see they're talking about global variables you know global scope getting polluted that's the
reason why IIFE was helping them but I'll I can talk in depth but it's not a right point of time
to talk in that or talk about that but I hope this is hoisting clear is hoisting concept clear
and how let wire and const is working with them
okay so if this thing is clear right I have one point one thing that I have to address okay
since
let's say I I'll give you one short example
okay it's a reference data type
not yes okay let's say I have a const object
inside this object let's say I have again uh things like let's say name so I have unketh
and let's say I have last name
as tivari
first name as unketh and last name as tivari
as unketh and last name as tivari now let's say I create an object one
that's object two and I assign this object and I say that object two dot first name
equal to let's say
with them
and object two dot last name as sharma
and I try to say that console dot log of object console dot log of object
so I just want you to you know uh think of it like what would be the output of this one
just guys think of this one like what would be the output of this one
guys do I have your attention just think of this one
what would do the output for this one like if I let's say this is this will return us
uh surely an object okay if we'll have first name and last name just think uh whether it will be
unketh tivari for both the things uh no it is it is going to print that uh akash
so let's see this if you think both the names will be printed uttam sharma twice uh dhigatses
uttam sharma twice how many of you think uh both the names if you think both the names give me
thumbs up if you think uttam sharma twice give me thumbs down guys
I say six and four let's let's let's explore this what's happening behind the scenes
okay now
uh okay I made a messed up here I use small thing here so all all of you who have told me two
two names that's click correct but if I do this thing if I do this thing do you see this uh like
if I do this thing do you see this uh like both the times I've said that I have updated object two
but it is updating object one also
right both the times it is printing only uttam sharma
do you think it's correct or this is what we are expecting
no right so people who gave me thumbs up earlier who were thinking like both the names will be
printed if you go back what was this file name guys what was this file name something called
as a reference data type right now let's understand so one thing when I introduced in last class
I introduced in last class there is something called primitive
and there's something called as reference
so all the primitives right their memory
is in stack
and you can say this is a temporary once your stack is cleared this will be removed but here
for the reference they their memory
is stored in heap
so let's say if I rightly explain through pictographical representation
let's say you have something like let a equal to 10
then let b equal to first name
okay and what we are doing we are saying let c equal to b and I'm saying c dot first name
okay equal to ankit so I'm doing this
once if I'm doing this let's see what's happening from the inside a call stack itself right so when
I talked about in terms of memory is something like call stack and there is something like heap area
right now once the memory is created execution starts a value will be here 10 then b
value since it's a primitive data type primitive type okay when you go for b
it's a reference data type since it's an object b will always point to something in the heap area
here it will have an object call first name
now once you go for c right once you go for c c equal to b then this c is also referring to the
same thing but it is not there's no like there is no new object being created you know there's
something called pass by value pass by reference I'll cover this in future class in the next class
pass by reference I'll cover this in future class and we'll have good amount of time to
understand this topic but this is something being applied here but if you see for the b
and c are acting on the same object but address is same right where this object is located in the
heap this is stack and this is it
now when I'm doing c dot first name remember the c dot first name I'm accessing this object
I'm seeing that c dot first name
equal to Ankit when I'm doing this this particular object will be updated as Ankit
now both b and c are pointing to this object and name is Ankit right that's the reason why
that's the reason why here both the places I'm getting this Uttam Sharma as the output
instead of Ankit Tiwari and Uttam Sharma is this point clear like how memory is stored
for the parameters and how memory is stored for reference data type guys
why this wasn't working
if anyone's still having any problem give me thumbs down if it is overwhelming let me know
guys I'll push it to the next class
no right overwhelming okay
yeah I'll I'll talk to you and get this one in the doubt session this one okay but
let's forget all the other things but this point is clear like what is you know last
class we discussed primitive and non-primitive data types reference data types reference data
types have a memory associated with the object and each time you try to assign a new variable
same object new object won't be created in the heap but you will have the same address
of location and once you update this the value will be updated in the object and this is how
it is working but if you want to fix this if you want to fix this issue how can you do it
is something like I want to talk about this one because I'll use one operator one operator here
which I'll pick it up in the next class as a first topic and that operator I'm defining it here
here what I'm doing it here is something called a spread operator okay
I'll explain the behind the scene concepts in the later classes but I'll explain
I'll talk about this one operator in the next class like we are I'm trying to introduce one
by one topic let's say if I execute this one again if you see Ankit Tiwari and Uttam Sharma
both are printed differently firstly so we are solving this problem earlier we were able to see
only like Uttam Sharma being printed twice but this is fixing that issue isn't this guy I hope
that you understood it but I'll pick it up something called as spread operator as the
first topic of the next class okay but guys do let me you know repeat everything that we have
discussed in the class because the content whatever is been planned for today is covered
because I wanted to give you more time on hoisting because for the beginners right
it's really difficult to process or if someone is you know having a hands-on with JavaScript
they might be it might be easy for them to process the other content but let's explore
let's let me revise all the things that have discussed okay now so firstly we started with
an array which is again a reference data type where we have discussed of six methods push pop
shift and unshift earlier one is to add and remove elements at the end of the array shift and shift
is used to add at the starting of an array then we discuss something called a slice which is used
to cut a particular piece of an array and store it in a new variable such that you're not disturbing
the existing array okay and we went for splice splice is somewhere used to add remove and replace
all the things inside an array okay which is existing the current copy of an array like you
can add it and it takes a four or five parameters depending upon the things that you are declaring
but you have two parameters as a mandatory first one what is the starting index where you want to
start splice from and then how many number of elements you want to delete or replace and then
like if you are adding elements you're supposed to like give zero like as a deleting element
and you can add how many elements you want to add it from there that particular index
it will manipulate it similarly for the splice if you want to delete it you can say that hey
static from index one delete the three items then for replacing it you say that static from zero
the index replace two items 2l and 13 as like from one end to us 2l and 13 okay i hope this was clear
and then we went to object we created something object called as captain america where we had
all types of you know data types that we have discussed function boolean objects arrays and
everything then we discussed like how can you access a key for like a particular value from
an object using a dot operator or executing a function then we have seen about how can you
update a particular you know value if you want to in an object and then how can you add it if you
want to add a new key value pair inside an object and similarly how you can delete it
right then we went on to understand something for topic called as hoisting we start with an
analogy where we have seen that hey even if you try to initialize you know access the variable
before initialization surprisingly it was we are not getting undefined but whereas we were getting
something error as undefined now for that understanding we try to you know understand
the memory execution phase sorry code execution phase where which happens in two phases memory
creation and code execution so firstly for each of the variables we have we have understood that
hey all the values will be initialized with a default value called undefined and functions
will also be initialized with the memory and when code is executed actually in the real time
their values will be assigned for each function execution we also understood that hey new execution
context will be created for the each step right whenever you're calling a new function then
understanding this code execution phase we figured out that hey during memory creation phase itself
all the values are initialized the default values and defined so we were able to get
undefined value instead of not different in that example then we have seen this with example of
var keywords then we went to something called as esx and esx issues where like we have introduction
of let and const this let and const were solving the problem of you know where you see like even
if you write down like console like you initially you are trying to access a value before
declaring it or re-initializing it then this particular fields were throwing us error that
hey you cannot access element a or any value like this one before initialization
right this is the error we were getting so this let and const have improved the way we can receive
when errors like like you can you can say error handling that's because
they were doing this inside something called as a temporal dot zone because that in that zone
these values are not by default available to you know access accesses until unless your
declaration is executed in the code okay so this is something we figured out that hey let and
const are still being hoisted that we are understood by this example that if you see here
we see that values are still being assigned some default value values unavailable back then once
you execute it the value is still being assigned so memory creation and code execution steps are
still being followed but here these are done these are being done in that something called
as temporal dead zone okay it's a zone where you don't really have an undefined value because we
have seen you know when you go for data types you can have null key undefined key or number
string boolean right these are the list of things that you can assign to any variable
but here if you see that it doesn't have any those values are assigned so it doesn't allow
you to access it throws an error so this is what we have understood today in terms of hoisting
in terms of how let and const are varying with respect to var and what are the fixes we got
in es6 right so i hope guys you enjoyed the class and learned things in depth in terms of js
so guys with your permission if these things are clear can i start the doubt session
thank you guys so i'm starting this doubt session guys
uh i hope you guys enjoyed it like uh did you find today's class interesting
like from behind the scenes concept
cool because i see few people side completely beginners are they are facing too much challenge
uncle do you want me to unmute you
it's fine okay so uh i would suggest uncle is that uh yeah rewatch it and also whatever
articles have been right uh go through them i'll also link it i'll share it in the reading
material such that you can go and refresh that uh i'll see if i can add an image of this
core memory execution and all those uh images in the self-study uh in the this like we had it
add it for this one uh like you know position property
yeah uh muneshwar please do do go through it okay so i'll try to create image for code execution
phase so that you can people relate it but uh since i'm completely occupied uh with too many
works this week uh maybe i'll do it in some day and i'll share it with you guys but i assure you
that i'll try make you uh you know put efforts towards so that you can understand the concepts
towards so that you can understand the concepts and be comfortable with the topics that we are
actually having in curriculum okay yeah do rewatch it and kids
so yeah yeah yeah surely i'll you can ask me anytime so are you able to follow up on kids
with the assignments and everything yeah do share me the contest question which you
faced challenge if you have it i can take it up i can take it up right away
okay till html you were able to uh because it was easy yeah i agree uh css part is a bit
difficult but you have to keep revising so it will take time some bit like take it slowly
don't put too much pressure uh take it step by step uh you know keep revising it
i'll push the code guys and give me a second
i'll update read me firstly
class nine
thing
so
arrays splice then we have discussed something on object
in depth then we have covered hoisting with where and let and const
then we covered a reference data type
manipulation and we have to start with rest and spread after operator in the next class
get
yeah some bit pushed the code you can check in the repository
okay do you have questions
uh like contest question if you have it i can take it up
because i might need question i have to see if i can access it
give me a second okay you're typing it uh okay
so one thing okay sure sure sure take your time one thing you can do is like if you have face
instantly uh because i've seen in group right uh people are helping each other and i've seen
many people are you know doing that i really appreciate uh you know people uh somebody i
guess who was answering the questions so please try to do uh you know help out each other it will
really uh beneficial to you and me everyone right i might not be able to take everything there
but i'll try my best to answer questions
so
okay yeah so which one do you think right
so this was a question
i think two and four right even i think it at first instance uh
okay
hmm so one of the you know uh i would agree that a fourth uh statement have to be updated
properly but second one is obviously right everyone is agreeing right fourth option
what do you think on the fourth option css inheritance are to applicable to only child element
is how many of you think that hey fourth option is a bit confusing
right because
right so
uh thank you for pointing out actually
because i have to update the fourth option we should go with the second option actually
because that's hard uh when you go from top to bottom right you read it
second second one is right right according to the contest or what everyone have given
yes i didn't see the contest questions but
okay yeah because what happens is uh like when you go read from the top to bottom
whatever first thing option you see that you can tick it up because we will i'll address this one
to fix this fourth question uh right you know inheritance is by default only applicable to child
elements and to the body tag everything is a child element right if you add anything to
the body tag by default or html tag all things should be applicable so
thank you for pointing this kabir i i'll try to you know that's the reason why i copied it once
i read it i copied it such that i can give to the team i they can update it
uh anything else guys
uh but you think i think is right now by both answers are correct yeah yeah i agree with you
it's not your mistake both the things are right itself whatever you're thinking that's right
that's the reason why i've asked people to say right uh how many of you think that
fourth point is also right you see the peers are also agreeing with your point not only me
okay
so even if i put it in this one let's say chat gpt
that's also suggesting a second point
so
okay anyways guys i'll update and talk to you on this one okay anything else
so uh if you see i got an answer i asked it to verify the fourth option so it says that
it not might be correct completely accurate because inheritance works in both directions
from parent to child elements and from child to the parents element
directions from parent to child elements and from child to the parents element
certain properties from the parents but not limited to child elements in a reading from the parents
under certain circumstances so i'll explore that
okay
it's contradicting contradicting it but anyways there's any other questions
any other questions do you have any other questions
okay
as if there are no questions can we close the call for today
a final thumbs up guys good night guys take care and
see you on thursday uh i'll let you know the new instructor who will be assigned on thursday and
and i'll come back on next saturday to take this up and cut this question
to ping team yeah uh for three classes because i have to take care of my personal
you know like recommendations like i have uh my sister's marriage so i'm going to attend that and
i have too many things to take care so i'll be on leave okay so
so hello guys then good night have good night take care see you on thursday
uh hope you have enjoyed thank you kabir
bye bye guys good night
you